Ruhama Yared

Full Stack Software Engineer | (571) 340.7028 | ruhamayared1@gmail.com | Alexandria, VA | in/ruhama-yared | github.com/ruhamayared | ruhamayared.com | decodedcode01.blogspot.com

Executive Summary

Mission driven programmer currently working on a COVID-19 testing and reporting application as part of a federal government program with the FDA. Collaborating with a cross-functional team of software engineers, UX designers, and data scientists alongside industry experts and mentors. Pivoting from a progressive career of 8+ years, teaching STEM to diverse and underserved populations.

Skills

Languages - JavaScript, TypeScript, HTML, CSS, Python, Go, Rust, SQL | Libraries and Frameworks - Bootstrap, Tailwind CSS, React, Node.js, Express.js, jQuery, Django, FastAPI, Flask, Echo

Database & other - MongoDB, Mongoose, PostgresSQL, Amazon Web Services (AWS) | **Other** - Responsive Web Design, JSON, RESTful APIs, GitHub, Slack, Trello, Visual Studio Code, Excel, frontend, backend web development,

Interpersonal Skills: Independent, creative problem-solver with autonomy, empathy, and engaging communication, growth mindset

Professional Experience

The Opportunity Project 2023, Remote | Sprint Participant – Software Engineering Lead

05/2023 - Present

- Collaborate with a team of 15+ Software Engineers, UX/UI Designers, UX Researchers, and Data Scientists and Data Analysts on The Opportunity Project, led by the US Census Bureau, the US Department of Commerce, and the FDA
- Develop a secure, responsive website using React to enable users to track their COVID test results
- Design and implement robust privacy choices and information to ensure user confidence in the handling of their health data
- Co-create a comprehensive data storage plan using AWS (Amazon Web Services) with team members, harmonizing with other health data and ensuring secure aggregation and accessibility
- Troubleshoot issues, contribute ideas, and work closely with team members to deliver a high-quality final product that has clean, maintainable, and testable code

Fairfax County Public Schools, Alexandria, VA | Mathematics Teacher Alexandria City Public Schools, Alexandria, VA | Mathematics Teacher Nysmith School for the Gifted, Herndon, VA | Mathematics Teacher

08/2021 - Present 08/2019 - 06/2020 08/2014 - 06/2017

- Coached peers on new Learning Management Systems to integrate modern processes and optimize workflow efficiency
- Collaborated with cross-functional teams weekly to address collective challenges, and discussed and applied new research and technologies, resulting in a measurable rise in student engagement
- Curated over 100+ supplemental resources that met organizational and technical specifications and accessibility standards, resulting in increased student fluency and test scores
- Created project-based formal assessments to evaluate learner progress, resulting in 100% pass rate for state standardized tests in 2021
- Communicated with stakeholders through LMS, calls, and emails, resulting in improved parent and stakeholder engagement
- Implemented instructional design methods such as PADDIE, resulting in enhanced student learning and retention by over 50%
- Transformed curriculum development by incorporating technology, reducing planning time by 25%

Projects 09/2022 – 04/2023

Healing Pages - Full-stack CRUD application for personal journal management with rich text formatting

Crafted an engaging and user-friendly CRUD app using Go, Echo, TypeScript, React, Vite, Postgres, and ReactQuill, enabling
effortless creation and management of richly formatted journal entries

The Spice App - Full-stack CRUD app designed to keep track of all the exotic spices that are out there

- Engineered a dynamic CRUD application utilizing Python, Django, TypeScript, React, and Tailwind CSS
- Orchestrated an agile development process that prioritized critical features and culminated in the successful deployment of the app

Road Trip Buddy - Full-stack web application that allows users to seamlessly manage road trip destinations

- Played a key role in the creation of a MERN-based web application, adhering to project specifications and wireframes, utilizing GitHub for version control and collaboration
- Implemented MongoDB, Express.js, React, and Node.js to build a modular application, incorporating a one-to-many data model
- Facilitated Agile practices, including Scrum and Trello board tracking, and pair-programmed RESTful API routes

Education

General Assembly | Remote | Software Engineering Immersive
University of Virginia | Charlottesville, VA | Master of Public Policy
Goucher College | Baltimore, MD | Bachelor of Arts in Education, Mathematics

09/2022 - 04/2023

08/2017 - 05/2019

08/2009 - 05/2013